טוב, Tov, today's דף daf where we're up at our supposed דף
daf is דף ח, Daf Ches, we pick up at the bottom
of ז עמוד א. Zayin Amud Aleph. We're going to start with
the בבלי Bavli because there's very little ירושלמי Yerushalmi today and if
we get a chance we'll do it at the end because it
ties into the דף ח. Daf Ches. So let's see how far
we get there. Okay, so we pick up at the bottom of
ז עמוד א Zayin Amud Aleph and the גמרא's Gemara just dealt
with a whole discussion about ביצוע bitzua versus דין, din, binding arbitration
slash compromise as opposed to justice, and then some digressions about talking
about popular sayings and how they connect to verses. And we pick
up with the two dots about eight lines from the bottom on
ז עמוד א. Zayin Amud Aleph. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר
רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, כל דיין
שדן דין אמת לאמיתו, kol dayan shedan din emes l'amito, משרה שכינה
בישראל. mashre Shechina beYisrael. So if you judge the proper, so here
it's not choosing between... אמת לאמיתו...
emes l'amito... I know.
Here it's not choosing between דין din versus compromise, but you're already
operating within the context of justice and the importance of obviously doing
it right. And we had that whole discussion before, the witnesses have
to know before whom they're appearing, the judges have to know before
whom they're judging, you have to really understand that you're like representing
God and trying to bring a sense of justice in the world.
So any judge who actually does אמת לאמיתו, emes l'amito, truth to
its truth, okay which is an interesting double language. I would remind
us of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that spoke about part of the idea
of truth has to do with process and not just result. Anyway,
משרה שכינה בישראל. mashre Shechina beYisrael. You what?
עיין זה עיין
זה.
Ayin zeh
Ayin zeh.
Yeah there you go. Exactly, you cause the Divine Presence to dwell
among Israel. שנאמר, Shene'emar, אלוהים נצב בעדת אל, Elokim nitzav ba'adat El,
when does God dwell in the presence of the community of God?
בקרב אלוהים ישפוט, Bekerev Elokim yishpot, in the presence of God do
you judge, when justice is being done, then God is able to
dwell on earth. וכל דיין שאינו דן דין אמת לאמיתו, Vekol dayan
she'eino dan din emes l'amito, but if you do not come you
know judge the truth the justice to its utmost truth, גורם לשכינה
שתסתלק מישראל. gorem laShechina shetistalek miYisrael. You cause the Divine Presence to
be withdrawn. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
משוד עניים מאנקת אביונים, mishod aniyim me'ankat evyonim, from the despoiling of
the poor and the outcry of the needy, עתה אקום יאמר השם,
ata akum yomar Hashem, now I will rise up says God. So
you can say rise up to do vengeance, but actually rise up
to leave that is to withdraw myself. ואמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יונתן... Ve'amar Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan... Mike
go ahead. כל דיין שנוטל מזה ונותן לזה, Kol dayan shenotel mizeh
venoten lizeh, any judge that takes from one and gives to the
other שלא כדין, shelo kedin, inappropriately, so here it's perverting justice. The
first פסוק pasuk I sort of echoed the sense of not engage
sort of not you know sort of like ignoring the injustice that
is being done, maybe sort of also the sense of the judge
that decides to recuse himself so as not to get in trouble
with the you know... recuse? Yes... not get in trouble with the
powerful people you know and so on. You know, so that's like
you're ignoring the outcry of the poor. This one seems to echo
you know just the sense of actually perverting justice, judging
incorrectly. So כל דיין שנוטל מזה ונותן לזה, kol dayan shenotel mizeh
venoten lizeh, who takes away from one gives to the other שלא
כדין, shelo kedin, not you know which is in a way that's
against the law, הקדוש ברוך הוא נוטל ממנו נפשו. Hakadosh Baruch Hu
notel mimenu nafsho. God will demand from him his soul. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
אל תגזול דל כי דל הוא ואל תדכא עני בשער. al tigzol
dal ki dal hu ve'al tedake ani basha'ar. Do not steal from
the poor because he is poor, don't feel you can get away
with it, and do not trample down on the poor person in
the gate, and again presumably how do we know this is not
just talking about somebody who steals? Because presumably the word שער sha'ar
here is understood to evoke the sense of justice, right, like לוט
יושב בשער סדום, Lot yoshev besha'ar Sedom, that was a place that
justice was done. כי השם יריב ריבם, Ki Hashem yariv rivam, God
will come to fight their fight, וקבע את קובעיהם נפש, vekava es
koveihem nafesh, and rob from those who steal from them, rob their
soul. Okay, so again the real great need that if you're dealing
with to judge properly. ואמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן,
Ve'amar Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, לעולם יראה דיין עצמו
כאילו חרב מונחת לו בין ירכותיו, le'olam yireh dayan atzmo k'ilu cherev
munachas lo bein yarchosav,
a judge should see himself like a sword is between his legs
is between his thighs, וגיהנום פתוחה לו מתחתיו, veGehinnom pesucha lo mitachtav,
and גיהנום Gehinnom is open below him. So this is really encouraging
to want to be a judge, okay, but you have to really
understand the consequence of judging incorrectly. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says, הנה
מטתו שלשלמה שישים גיבורים סביב לה, hinei mitaso shelishlomo shishim gibborim seviv
la, sixty here's Shlomo's bed sixty mighty people surrounding
it,
מגיבורי ישראל, migibborei Yisrael, כולם אחוזי חרב, kulam achuzei cherev, מלומדי מלחמה,
melumdei milchama, knowing the war, איש חרבו על ירכו, ish charbo al
yerecho, each person's sword against their thigh, מפחד בלילות. mipachad baleilos. Fear
of the night, מפחדה של גיהנום שדומה ללילה. mipachada shel Gehinnom shedomeh
lalaylah. Fear of גיהנום Gehinnom if you rule incorrectly. I don't know
how we interpret this to be specifically about a case of being
a judge, you know רש"י Rashi actually speaks about the גיבורים, gibborim,
רש"י Rashi says תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, you know מלומדי מלחמה, melumdei
milchama, מלחמתה של תורה. milchamta shel Torah. So that has classic evokes
the whole sense of like learning תורה Torah in the בית מדרש
Beit Midrash and so on, but we're specifically applying it to you
know the consequence of judging incorrectly will be
will be severe. Okay. Judge justice in the morning and save the
one who is being robbed from those from the hand of the
oppressor. וכי בבוקר דני ובכל יומא אין דני, vachi baboker danni vechol
yoma ein danni, you only judge in the morning? Don't you judge
the whole day? Okay, maybe you don't judge at night, that's a
question, but you certainly don't just judge in the morning. אלא
אם ברור לך דבר כבוקר אמריהו, ella im barur lach davar kaboker
amreihu, if it's as clear to you as the morning, like so
you know, when morning breaks, when dawn breaks, it's all very clear
and it's a very obvious difference between black and white, you know,
light and darkness, then say it. ואם לאו אל תאמריהו, ve'im lav
al tomreihu, and if don't, don't say it. Which of course is
a little bit, you know, points out to a challenge because that
doesn't mean that justice will be served, right? If it seems to
you like, okay, I'm not a hundred percent sure that this person
is right, it seems to me they're right, so what am I
supposed to do, not render judgment? So then that also means that
justice might not be served. Okay, if you, and now הלכה halakha
has ways of dealing with cases of doubt like המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi mechaveiro alav harayah. If I'm not sure that you're right
then, you know, then I say okay, then the burden of proof
is on the other side and we're just going to have to
let, you know, this person won't have to pay out. But that
might be perverting justice for all I know, right? So it's interesting
that does, you know, saying that type of thing that it has
to be a hundred percent clear to you does not necessarily ensure
that justice is going to get done.
Yeah, that's what I was wondering about before. דיין שנותן לו dayan
shenotein lo from to this to that בית דין, beit din, does
it mean that like you tried the best you can, you were
wrong?
Right, so exactly, this has to be balanced against the earlier גמרא,
Gemara, which the גמרא Gemara says, so let's say, so what do
I need to deal with all of this? And it says אין
לו לדיין אלא מה שעיניו רואות, ein lo ladayan ela mah she'einav
ra'ot, right? So it has to mean that you're, you know, you're
trying the best you can. Okay, but you know, but
sometimes פוסקים poskim use the phrase אין לו לדיין אלא מה שעיניו
רואות ein lo ladayan ela mah she'einav ra'ot to specifically say, you
know, that you don't know the facts a hundred percent, but you
have to judge the facts as best as you, as best as
you can assess them. Right? So but, you know, so you have
to sort of balance statements like, a) statements about like you should
be afraid to judge wrongly with like no, you actually if you
do the best you can, you're okay. And statements about you have
to be a hundred percent with אין לו לדיין אלא מה שעיניו
רואות. ein lo ladayan ela mah she'einav ra'ot. You know, those statements
live in tension with one another. Okay. So anyway,
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן מהכא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan meihacha, אמור לחכמה אחותי את, emor lachochmah achoti at,
say to wisdom you are my sister. אם ברור לך הדבר כאחותך
שאסורה לך, im barur lach hadavar kachotecha she'asurah lach, if it's as
clear to you the ruling as it's clear that a man is
not allowed to have sex with his sister, so then אמריהו, amreihu,
then give the judgment. ואם לאו אל תאמריהו, ve'im lav al tomreihu,
and if not, don't say it. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, עשרה שיושבין בדין, asarah sheyoshvim badin, ten people
that sit in judgment, כולו תלוי בצוואר כולן. kulo talui betzavar kulan.
They all the yoke, you know, or the קולר, kolar, the chains,
you know, sort of the neck brace or whatever, sits, you know,
hangs on all of their throats.
עשרה שיושבין בדין? asarah sheyoshvim badin?
Why, you mean when you have ten people? Yeah, that's also interesting
because now we're maybe moving away just from a case of a
בית דין beit din to actually like פוסקנינג. paskening. Right? So we'll
see that, you know, let's keep on reading. But that's good that
you noticed that. Ten is not a standard size of a בית
דין. beit din. Okay. Everybody sort of shares in the responsibility. פשיטא,
peshita, of course everybody shares in the responsibility. You know, so it's
לא צריכא אלא לתלמיד היושב לפני רבו, lo tzericha ela letalmid hayosheiv
lifnei rabbo, it means that even if somebody is there is a
student in front of their רבי. Rebbe. So, and if then רש"י
Rashi sort of ties it back to what we said before, you
know, if the person could have said something and didn't say something,
they bear some of that responsibility. So this, if you just took
it this way, basically means that if a lot of people were
involved and they're all getting it wrong, it's not a basis of
sort of of displacing responsibility. Hey, what is it my fault, other
people were there? No, you know, if it's, if you're פוסקנינג paskening
incorrectly, you're all to blame. Okay. But the גמרא Gemara now also
so switches a gear a little bit and talks about a sense
of don't say, don't use this as a basis to displace responsibility,
but that actually this is a way of also lightening the burden
to some degree, and which is the next line of the גמרא,
Gemara, which is רב הונא כי הוה אתי דינא לקמיה, Rav Huna
ki hava atei dina lekameih, when a judgment would come in front
of him, a case would come in front of him, מכניף ומייתי
עשרה רבנן, michneif umaitei asarah rabanan, there you go, there's your ten,
would gather ten rabbis together מבי רב mibei rav from like the
ישיבה, yeshiva, and אמר להו כי היכי דלימטיי שיבא מכשורא, amar lehu
ki heichi de'limtiyei shiva mikashura, in order that a splinter from the
beam should go to everyone. That way we should all share in
the burden of the responsibility. So this is the opposite. Don't say
just because a lot of people are there, hey it's not my
fault, everybody else was there too. But here it's actually saying if
you're about to judge and you have a hesitation about whether you,
about how you should be judging, get other people together so that
you can all sort of take a portion of that responsibility. This
actually you find in פוסקים poskim sometimes when they're ruling on a
case and they're a little bit hesitant, they sometimes will say I'm
not going to sort of go this way unless I, you know,
here's my opinion, but I won't say this unless I can get
other rabbis, you know, five other rabbis to sign on. three other
rabbis, ten other rabbis to sign on that we should all take
a שיבא מכשורא. shiva mi-kishora. We should take a splinter of the
beam. We should all sort of share in the responsibility. It's actually
also interesting whatever they've done these
sociological studies about like about how decision making is made when you
have like groups as opposed to individuals, and they sort of basically
like assumed that when you're having groups or something that people would
make
more... what was the assumption? I think the assumption was was that
people thought that groups would be more conservative because, oh no I
should have looked up the study. Anyway, there was some assumption that
I think they thought that people would be more conservative in a
group because like the different opinions would like balance themselves out, you
know, but they actually found out that like it didn't work that
way, that like you know people like people were able to influence
decisions of groups and actually avoid taking personal responsibility for the decision
because it was a group but would still sort of have their
influence exerted on it.
Yeah, anyway. But it is interesting, you know, sort of what you
know, what this means. It means sort of like that it sort
of it echoes back, this understanding sort of echoes back to the
idea of don't be a דיין יחידי, dayan yachidi, don't judge by
yourself, don't think all the truth rests in you. If you're going
to make an important decision, you know, have other people involved so
that you know you hear other perspectives, other people can sort of
share in the decision making process. Although in this case right here
he took ten unnamed rabbis from a ישיבה, yeshiva, you know, it
sounds like it's one imagines that they mostly defer to him, right,
you know, it doesn't sound like it was a really of sort
of like a vigorous debate. Right? So it does sort of make
you question how much does that really translate into sharing of a
responsibility.
So it says like this, רב אשי כי הוי אתי טרפה לקמיה
Rav Ashi ki hava ati tereifa lekameih when he would have a
טרפה tereifa and this gets also to Michael's question about ten, are
we talking about ten as a בית דין beit din or we're
just talking about like in the process of consulting in terms of
פסק, psak, when a טרפה tereifa would come for him,
מכניף ומייתי להו לכולהו טבחי דמתא מחסיא. makhnif u-maiti lehu le-khulhu tavkhei
de-Mata Mechasya. This works better, you know. He would gather up all
of the שוחטים shochtim of
the city of מתא מחסיא Mata Mechasya ואמר כי היכי דלימטיין שיבא
מכשורא ve-amar ki heichi di-limteian shiva mi-kishora so everybody should get a
little bit of a splinter of the beam. Okay, now it makes
sense. If you're getting the שוחטים, shochtim, right, so A, they're the
ones to whom the judgment affects, so and B, they have expertise.
Right? So now that process actually makes sense. Right? If you're going
to bring in the people to whom your פסק psak will affect,
you're going to hear their concerns or their opinions or whatever. Wait,
if you פסקן pasken this way, it's going to mean A, B,
and C, you know, and it's so it may make you like
rethink your פסק psak because sometimes פסק, psak, you know, has an
you know is in relationship to how it's impacting people and you
know whatever. And B, they're bringing also their expertise to it. So
that this process actually makes a lot more sense than the previous
one about what the benefit is of something like that. You wouldn't
שיבא מכשורא shiva mi-kishora then.
You could have said like he wasn't sure, you know, he's not
a שוחט shochet maybe. Right? So it's more that he doesn't know.
No no no. He knew as far as you
know he
you know he could have פסקןed pasken by himself, but you want
to make sure that you're hearing everybody's perspective and getting all the
opinions and getting everybody brings their own perspective and their own knowledge
to the table. Yeah, well right, exactly. But I don't but I
think responding to Michael, it's not like he didn't have sufficient knowledge
to פסקן. pasken. He did, but he still wanted to hear other
people who had different perspectives and different types of knowledge than he
did. Okay. כי אתא רב דימי אמר ki ata Rav Dimi amar
when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael said,
דרש נחמן בר כהן מאי דכתיב darash Nachman bar Kohen mai di-ketiv
what's meant by the verse מלך במשפט יעמיד ארץ ואיש תרומות יהרסנה.
melech be-mishpat ya'amid aretz ve-ish terumot ye-hersena. The king with justice will
establish you know the land but a man of gifts like you
know who takes bribes essentially will destroy it. So we're going to
read תרומות terumot as a כהן kohen and notice by the way
that he is saying he is רב נחמן בר כהן. Rav Nachman
bar Kohen. Okay so listen to this. אם דיין
דומה למלך שאינו צריך לכלום im dayan domeh le-melech she-eino tzarich le-khlum
if the judge is like a king that he doesn't need anything,
so he's all powerful, יעמיד ארץ ya'amid aretz he'll be able to
establish you know justice. Also rich right? Well we'll talk about what
this means in a minute. ואם דומה לכהן שמחזר בבית הגרנות ve-im
domeh le-kohen she-mechazer be-veit ha-granot
if he is an איש תרומות ish terumot somebody who accepts תרומה
teruma like a כהן kohen who has to go to one you
know from one threshing floor to the next to get his grain,
יהרסנה ye-hersena he will destroy it. Now what does this mean? What
are we talking about? So Michael thought and I actually also thought
it means if you're rich and self-sufficient and you don't need anybody's
favor and take bribes or whatever you know you're independent then you'll
be able to judge truly. But if you're dependent on other people
you know people you know people's goodwill and whatever and you're not
wealthy then obviously that will compromise the true sense of justice. That's
what תוספות Tosafot says. But רש״י Rashi says if you look at
רש״י's Rashi second narrow line, אם דומה דיין למלך שבקי בטיב דינים.
im domeh dayan le-melech she-baki be-tiv dinim. מלא חכמה כמלך
זה שהוא עשיר, umale chochma kemelech ze shehu ashir, okay, as opposed
to the כהן kohen שמחזר על הגרנות לשאול תרומתו ואז צריך לחשוב
לשאול בית. shemechazer al hagranot lishol trumato veaz tzarich lachshov lishol beis.
So if you, you know, if you really know your stuff, then
it'll be justice. But if you have to ask שאלות shaylos all
the time, of course it's a little interesting when you put that
in juxtaposition of what we just said, which is about consulting and
bringing other people in, so there's like a balance, right? There's somebody
who's like a real expert, you know, if you go
to a, to a doctor who's a real expert and he says,
you know, I advise you to get a second opinion, that doesn't
mean because I don't know my job, right? I could be an
expert neurosurgeon, but it's a very sensitive issue and you should, you'll
benefit yourself to hear somebody who also is an expert, right? So
you can be an expert who consults, or you can be somebody
who really doesn't know their job and who really doesn't have the
knowledge, the deep knowledge that they need, right, in order to judge
properly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
where were we? דבי נשיא אוקמי דיינא דלא הוה גמיר. debei nesi
ukmei dayana delo hava gmir.
So the house of the נשיא nasi
established a judge that did not really know. Now we're echoing back
the idea because you remember that what does, who's a יחיד מומחה?
yachid mumche? If he's גמיר וסביר, gmir vesavir, and we just spoke
here about being, this is also explained if this, like this is
why רש"י Rashi explained it this way, because it's about somebody who
really knows their stuff as opposed to the guy who's going around
and doesn't know anything and has to ask everybody, okay? So in
order to be a יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche, you have to be
a גמיר וסביר. gmir vesavir. You gotta know your stuff and also
have good analysis. And you have to, the question is do you
need to be נטילת רשות notel reshus from the נשיא nasi or
from the ריש גלותא? reish galusa? So here the נשיא, nasi, of
course, once it was clear that there was a system in place
where the political heads were appointing the judges, that's what נטילת רשות
notel reshus is. So you can discuss גמיר וסביר gmir vesavir without
the political appointment, but you can understand the flip happens a lot
too. You get the political appointment but you don't really know your
stuff, okay? And that's what happens here. So
דבי נשיא אוקמי דיינא, debei nesi ukmei dayana, they, they appointed a
judge, דלא הוה גמיר, delo hava gmir, he didn't know his stuff,
okay? אמרו ליה ליהודה בר נחמני מתורגמניה דריש לקיש. amru lei liyehuda
bar nachmani meturgamania dereish lakish. So, קום עליה באמורא. kum alei be'amora.
So, so I don't know who the אמרו ליה amru lei here
was, but somebody said to יהודה בר נחמני, Yehuda bar Nachmani, who
was the, who was the translator, you know, sort of the, the
one who would, as you know, the word תנא tanna and אמורא,
amora,
תנא tanna and אמורא amora could be the person, what we normally
think: רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, those are תנאים;
tannaim; אביי ורבא, Abaye veRava, those are אמוראים. amoraim. But תנא tanna
also refers, right, to the person who would memorize the statements of
the תנאים tannaim and repeat them. And אמורא amora would also refer
to the people who would come and, you know, be the essentially
the loudspeakers. You know, here I am, I, you know, I need
to, I'm going to דרשן darshan to these masses, you know, I
gotta save my voice. I take Michael, he's got a nice big
booming voice and we stand in front of the crowd and I
whisper my words to Michael and Michael booms it to everybody else,
so he's the אמורא. amora. Okay, that's another use of the word
אמורא. amora. So they said to שמואל בר נחמני, Shmuel bar Nachmani,
so they said to
יהודה בר נחמני Yehuda bar Nachmani who was the, who was the
translator or the probably the announcer of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, קום
עליה באמורא. kum alei be'amora. So they said go be this person's
אמורא, amora, this דיין dayan who's this now, you know, this court,
this guy who's a political appointee. So קם גחין עליה, kam gachin
alei, he whispered to him, ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי. velo amar
lei velo midi. So he got up, so, you know, it's like
this classic joke. You know the joke about the rabbi with the,
with the בעל עגלה, ba'al agala, you know, the, the wagon driver?
He goes town to town and he gives the same דרשה drasha
everywhere, right? And so the wagon driver after a while says like,
you know, I've heard you give that דרשה drasha a thousand times,
I know it by heart, I could give it. He says fine,
next time, next town we'll go to, you'll pretend you're the rabbi,
I'm the wagon driver and you give the דרשה. drasha. So the
wagon driver goes ahead and he gives the דרשה drasha and everybody
is so impressed. And then somebody asks a question. So he doesn't
know what to do. So he says, you know, that question is
so stupid, even my wagon driver can answer it. Okay, so anyway,
so here the guy got up, so you have the אמורא amora
who's probably pretty knowledgeable, the announcer, and you got the guy who's
the judge who doesn't know anything. So the judge whispers into the
אמורא's amora's ear, but he says nothing because he doesn't know, so
he just whispers nothing. Okay, so קם גחין עליה, kam gachin alei,
he whispered to him, ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי. velo amar lei
velo midi. He didn't say anything.
So it wasn't the אמורא amora didn't say anything?
No, the guy who's supposed to be the judge, he doesn't know
anything. Okay, so what did the אמורא amora do? Now the אמורא
amora had to make it up. So what did the אמורא amora
do? So פתח ואמר, pasach ve'amar, he opened and he said, הוי
אומר לעץ הקיצה, hoi omer la'etz hakitza, woe to the one who
says to the wood "wake up", עורי לאבן דומם, uri le'even domem,
stir yourself to the dead rock, to the silent rock, הוא יורה
הנה הוא תפוש זהב וכסף וכל רוח אין בקרבו, hu yoreh hinei
hu tafus zahav vachesaf vechol ruach ein bekirbo, he should be the
one who judge like he should be the one who judges? Behold,
he is holding on to gold and silver and he has no
spirit within him!
So basically he says this guy is an empty vessel, okay, but
he says it sounds like as if he was repeating what the
guy had just whispered to him. Okay, so אז עתיד הקדוש ברוך
הוא Az atid Hakadosh Baruch Hu in the end God להיפרע ממעמידין
l'hipara mimamidin ממעמידים. mimamidim. If not only is it the fault of
the appointee, it's the point of the fault of the one who
does the appointing. Okay God in the end will just you know
will take payment from those that appoint such
people, שנאמר she-ne'emar וה' בהיכל קדשו הס מפניו כל הארץ. v'Hashem b'heichal
kodsho has mipanav kol ha'aretz. God is in his holy sanctuary silence
before him all the land, and that actually follows this פסוק pasuk
that we just you know that we just read about those who
speak and don't know anything, you know, say to the empty stone
you know to speak and so on. So God will rise up
and will take vengeance on the land. Yes, exactly yes.
And הנשיא haNasi at this time would probably have been רבי יהודה
הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi.
Could be and that could be. I don't know.
Okay anyway, so how do you define וה' בהיכל?
v'Hashem b'heichal? No, just means if if land is being silenced it's
because God is going to come and to do justice. Okay.
Where were we? אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish כל המעמיד דיין
kol hamaamid dayan anybody who appoints a judge שאינו הגון she'eino hagun
that is not fitting כאילו נוטע אשרה בישראל ke'ilu noteia asherah b'Yisrael
it's like you plant a you know which actually by the way
was also the metaphor from that previous thing about the stone and
the wood and that held on to gold and silver, it was
sort of like about also like an idol, you know, an empty
an idol that has no power in it. So anybody who plants
who appoints a judge is like you plant an אשרה asherah an
idol a tree that's for idolatrous worship, which gets again to the
sense of, you know, that if you do justice you bring God,
you store שכינה בישראל, Shechinah b'Yisrael, you know you are doing God's
justice and God's work and establishing the world according to sort of
the way God you know the sense of right and wrong. So
if you appoint, you plant, like you know somebody in you know
you know to be the judge and they're not don't know what
they're doing, you're doing the opposite, you're driving God away, you're bringing
in idolatry as it were.
Also you could also say by the image before, you know, you
wind up giving authority and essentially like worship to things that are
empty, you know things that don't deserve that like a false idol.
Okay, כאילו נוטע אשרה ke'ilu noteia asherah שנאמר she-ne'emar as it says
שופטים ושוטרים תיתן לך shoftim v'shotrim titein l'cha וסמיך ליה v'samich lei
לא תיטע לך אשרה כל עץ. lo tita l'cha asherah kol eitz.
Right,
you should have make judges, don't plant idolatrous trees. Right, so by
not appointing proper judges it's like you are spreading idolatry. ואמר רב
אשי V'amar Rav Ashi ובמקום שיש תלמידי חכמים uv'makom sheyesh talmidei chachamim
and if there were sages there that could have served as the
judges and you're by bypassing them כאילו נטעו אצל מזבח. ke'ilu netao
eitzel mizbeach.
It's like you planted it right up against the altar, right up
against the place, like it's direct defiance
of
God and God's presence, שנאמר she-ne'emar אצל מזבח ה' אלהיך eitzel mizbeach
Hashem Elokecha
do not plant this אשרה asherah by the altar of God. Okay.
כתיב Ktiv לא תעשון אתי אלהי כסף ואלהי זהב lo taasun iti
elokei cheseph v'elokei zahav do not make of me or you know
against me gods of gold and gods of silver. אלהי כסף ואלהי
זהב הוא דלא עבדי Elokei cheseph v'elokei zahav hu d'la avdi what,
we can't make gods of gold and silver הא דעץ שרי ha
d'eitz shari but we can make idols of wood? אמר רב אשי
Amar Rav Ashi אלוה הבא בשביל כסף eloah haba bishvil cheseph
don't make a god that has the meaning don't make appoint an
authority over you that is has that position because of money that
they've paid. Okay so that's again like the שופט shofet is like
you know an authority on this earth and is supposed to be
representing God's authority and becomes in this position like a god. So
don't that position should not have it as one that you know
because they've paid money, אלוה הבא בשביל זהב eloah haba bishvil zahav
which is obviously clearly acknowledging what some of the realities were. רב
כי הוי אתי לבי דינא Rav ki hava ati l'bei dina now
so now we're done with sort of the sense of like the
weight of responsibility on the judge, the way in which that brings
justice to the world, but you know the way in which having
political appointees that don't know what they're doing pervert justice, and now
we're going to deal with the issue here about the question about
like the honor that sometimes is given to judges, which is presumably
why people wanted that position, but how does somebody who is doing
it righteously you know and for the right reasons how do they
deal with the sense that maybe their their motives will be impugned
because you're doing it for honor, how do they themselves deal with
not being influenced by the honor that they receive from this position.
So let's take a look. רב כי הוי אתי לבי דינא Rav
ki hava ati l'bei dina when Rav would come to the court
to be a judge אמר הכי amar hachi he would say the
following. ברעות נפשיה לקטלא נפיק B're'ut nafshiah l'katla nafik through
like my own desire I am exposing myself to death meaning if
I judge incorrectly you know I'll be deserving of death. So what
you know what type of crazy thing is this to do here
you know I'm making the decision to expose myself to the possibility
like my life is at risk. וצבי ביתיה לית הוא עביד Utzvei
beiteih leit hu avid and by coming here and being a judge
I'm not taking care of my family needs. It's not like I'm
going to work and I'm earning money and I'm taking you know
I'm not getting anything out of this I'm not helping pay for
the bills back at home.
וריקן לביתיה עייל V'reikan l'beiteih ayeil I'll return empty-handed to my house.
home, I won't, you know, gain from this process at all, okay?
ולוואי שתהא ביאה כיציאה velivai shetehei biah kiyitziah
and I just hope that when I you know, that that that
my coming is like my going meaning that when I'm able to
return I don't make things worse. Exactly.
So, so you know, so here it's like again was he making
this declaration to himself, to other people, but it was clear that
he was basically making it clear that I am not doing this
for, believe me, you know, I'm not doing this for any כבוד.
kavod. Okay, and I'm just doing this because I feel the responsibility
to do this. כי הוי חזי אמבוהא
בתריה ki havei chazi ambua basrei
when he saw after he would leave the court that there would
be like a whole crowd of people gathering to follow him like
whatever he said it didn't work, you know, people still gave him
honor, okay. ספרי? safrei? No, ספרי safrei is taken out. אמבוהא ambua
just means like a like a gathering of people, crowds of people.
אמר amar he said, so how did he deal with the fact
that this could go to your head, you know? So he said,
אם יעלה לשמים שיאו im yaaleh lashamayim seo if you're you know,
if you would if if if you rise up to heaven, you
know, כגללו לנצח יאבד kegilalo lanetzach yoved like your dung you will
ultimately be destroyed. What's the
שיאו? seo?
Yeah, what's the שיאו? seo? I forget, I looked it up. But
okay. But anyway, it means that if you rise up to heaven
in the end you'll, you know, no honor you get in this
world means anything, in the end we'll all turn to dung and
all be destroyed. Okay, so that's how he kept himself humble. מר
זוטרא חסידא mar zutra chasida מר זוטרא mar zutra the חסיד chasid
כי הוי מכתפי ליה בשבתא דרגלא ki havei michtafi lei beshabsa deregla
what they would do is they would carry him the word כתף
katef they would carry him on their shoulders, okay, people, everybody would
be sitting on the ground, okay, and then you know and if
you're and you're the rabbi you gotta get to the front in
order to give the דרשה drasha but like רש"י rashi explains also,
if you're old and you're moving very slowly, it's taking a long
time and everybody as you're walking everybody has to get up, you
know, whatever. So in order to move things along a little bit,
you have people, you know, they put him on their shoulders and
they would just, you know, carry him straight to the front of
the room very quickly. Okay, but still, but the reality then of
that experience is you're there way up top, you're being held aloft
and everybody else is below. Okay, so when they would do this
on the שבת shabbos of the רגל regel meaning on you know
on the שבת shabbos when he would give these דרשות. drashos. And
he's a judge? This is now we're dealing like with right, not
about being a דיין, dayan, right? It's about dealing with honor in
general, that's true, for your תורה, torah, not just about being a
דיין. dayan. Okay, so the so this was like the שבת shabbos
before, you know, in the period the month before the רגל regel
when he would give a big, masses of people gathered because they
would want to learn, you know, the הלכות halachos about about the
רגל. regel. אמר הכי, amar hachi, so here's what he said to
keep his himself humble. כי לא לעולם חוסן ואם נזר לדור דור
ki lo leolam chosen veim nezer lador dor because, you know, honor
is not whatever or like wealth is not forever and glory is
not for all generations. In the end this is all passing and
trivial and this doesn't mean anything.
דרש בר קפרא darash bar kappara מנא מילתא דאמרו רבנן mena milsa
deamru rabanan where do we get this thing that the rabbis said?
הוי מתון בדין. hevei masun badin. So that was dealing with the
issue about honor, okay. Now we're switching gears about how do you
know this idea that you should be slow to judgment, take your
time, you know, give yourself full amount of time before deliberate, thank
you.
It's interesting how he quotes from אבות avos for both.
Yeah, yeah, it's interesting, yeah. Where was the other quote of
אבות? avos? אל תהי דן יחידי, al tehi dan yechidi, good point.
Okay, דכתיב dechiv as it says, לא תעלה במעלות lo saaleh bemaalos
do not go up in steps. Like that's like a quick way
to bound up stairs, you know, and also like it's a sense
also steps also have a sense of like jumping over a certain
process, right? You know, when you go up a step, if you
go up a ramp, right, you're doing every step, you know, you
know every you know you're doing every part of the process, when
you when you go up a step you're jumping over stuff in
the middle.
That also has to do with modesty when they're...
Yeah, but that's not the דרשה drasha we're doing now. We're doing
the דרשה drasha about about about the sense of like being deliberate
and making sure you're you're you're touching every point that needs to
be touched. לא תעלה במעלות lo saaleh bemaalos וסמיך ליה ואלה המשפטים
אשר תשים לפניהם. usmich lei veeileh hamishpatim asher tasim lifneichem. Okay,
so in the in the process of justice don't, you know, don't
be making these leaps, you know, go slowly.
Okay, וסמיך usmich okay. אשר תשים asher tasim one minute, אמר רבי
אלעזר amar rabbi elazar מניין לדיין שלא יפסע על ראשי עם קודש?
minayin ledayan shelo yifsa al roshei am kodesh? How do you know
not to step over the heads of people?
Okay, this is like that example I gave you which is, you
know, everybody is sitting and you have to get to your seat,
so you have to like walk over where everybody is sitting, but
then it looks like you're stepping over or like you're stepping over
heads. I don't know if your grandmother ever told you, right, don't
walk over somebody? Ever know everybody ever heard that good בובע מעשה?
bubbe mayse? Okay, anyway. It sounds more superstitious.
Ah yes, I know.
That's not what we're talking about here. Okay, anyway, this is that
again should show, you know, it makes it seem like you're greater
than them, you're stepping on them, you're stepping over them, okay. שנאמר
לא תעלה במעלות. sheneemar lo saaleh bemaalos. וסמיך ליה ואלה המשפטים אשר
תשים. vesamich lei ve'eileh hamishpatim asher tasim. Okay, so these are the
judges you should place. So then don't go over them and step
over people in your capacity here as a judge. Again, that sense
about humility.
Okay, now, אשר תלמדם מיבעי ליה. asher telamdem mibaei lei. So now
the Gemara has a question. Why does it say אשר תשים, asher
tasim, you should place? Why doesn't it say that you should teach
them? So אמר רבי ירמיה ואיתימא רבי חייא בר אבא, amar Rabbi
Yirmiyah ve'isayma Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, אלו כלי הדיינים, eileh klei hadayanim,
ש-אשר תשים, she-asher tasim, those are like the instruments of the judges
for keeping people in place. Okay, for as we're going to see.
רב הונא כי הוה נפיק לדינא, Rav Huna ki hava nafik ledina,
when Rav Huna would go out to be a judge, אמר הכי,
amar hachi, he would say the following. אפיקו לי מאני חנותאי, afiku
li manei chanusai, take for me the vessels of my store, meaning
my like professional, you know, instruments. What would they be?
מקל ורצועה, makel u'retzuah, a staff and a like a strap, a
leather strap,
ושופרא וסנדלא, veshufra vesandala, and a shofar and a sandal. So the
staff and the strap is to give lashes. Of course it's funny,
you know, the judges wouldn't be the ones that would impose the
lashes, that's what you've got the שוטרים shotrim for. But symbolically, I
mean we still have like the gavel, right? You know, right? So
that's like, you know, sort of that sense of... and the shofar
is to put somebody in excommunication, and the sandal, Rashi says, is
for חליצה. chalitzah. I don't know why that of all the things.
It's not exactly the same genre as the rest. I don't know.
Anyway, to me, in this context, it makes me think of who
was it,
Khrushchev with the sandal?
Yeah, anyway. So, but the point is is that there's a responsibility
not just to render justice but sometimes, you know, you have to
also be involved in making sure it gets applied. And that requires
sometimes being harsh.
Yes, בית דין beis din has to order חרם cherem or lashes.
But חליצה, chalitzah, do you need a judge?
Yeah, I know, so that's interesting. You actually do. That was one
of the things in our first משנה, mishnah, but it's still funny
of all the things to mention. Okay, ואצוה את שופטיכם בעת ההיא.
va'atzaveh es shofteichem ba'es hahi.
So now we're going to continue with this. I commanded your judges
at that time. Actually this is parsha, next week's parsha. Okay, beginning
of
דברים. Devarim. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, excuse me, כנגד מקל
ורצועה תהא זריז. keneged makel u'retzuah tehei zariz. So ואצוה, va'atzaveh, the
command, means to be, you know, to be like careful and punctilious
regarding being a שופט, shofet, you know, imposing the justice, the מקל
makel and the רצועה. retzuah. So Rashi says, what does it mean
תהא זריז? tehei zariz? So Rashi says,
wait a minute, ועל מה זריז? על המקל ועל הרצועה שיהיו מטילין
אימה על הציבור לשם שמים. ve'al mah zariz? Al hamakel ve'al haretzuah
sheyihyu metilin eimah al hatzibur leshem shamayim. So Rashi says it means
you got to actually own that responsibility of, you know, making people
fearful and whatever and, you know, people need to respect and listen
to the judges. I mean, you know, the fact they say, you
know, talk speak softly and carry a carry a what is it
and carry a big stick. You know, if you if you do
it well, you don't have to use the stick, right? If you
you just have to carry it, right? But you got to get
people to think that you're serious about it and you're prepared to
use it. So anyway, so Rashi says it's about owning that responsibility
to really make people properly afraid and respectful and fearful. תוספות Tosafos
says תהא זריז tehei zariz a little bit in the opposite direction.
שלא להטיל אימה על הציבור לרדותם יותר מדי. shelo lehatil eimah al
hatzibur leradosam yoser midai. It's in the opposite direction. Yes, you got
to do it, but be careful not to go overboard. All right,
so it's all about striking the right balance.
Striking, ha-ha. Okay, now,
now, now we're going to continue to דרשן darshan these פסוקים pesukim
here in דברים Devarim since we're talking about responsibilities of judges. We're
going to continue to look at these פסוקים pesukim in the beginning
of דברים Devarim in terms of what their implications are.
שמוע בין אחיכם ושפטתם צדק, shamoa bein achichem ushfatetem tzedek, hear between
your brethren and judge righteously. אמר רבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Chanina, אזהרה
לבית דין שלא ישמע דברי בעל דין קודם שיבא בעל דין חבירו.
azharah lebeis din shelo yishma divrei baal din kodem sheyavo baal din
chaveiro. Where do you know that a court cannot start listening to
one of the litigants before the other litigant appears?
Because it says שמוע בין אחיכם. shamoa bein achichem. It has to
be when you're between your brethren, when both sides are represented. ואזהרה
לבעל דין שלא יטעים דבריו לדיין קודם שיבא בעל דין חבירו. ve'azharah
lebaal din shelo yat'im devarav ledayan kodem sheyavo baal din chaveiro. Similarly,
the so not only is the court not allowed to, but as
a litigant, you're not allowed to. If they're not doing their responsibility,
you are also obligated to not present your case before the other
one comes. קרי ביה נמי שמע בין אחיכם, kari beih nami shama
bein achichem, not just שמוע shamoa to listen, but to make heard.
When you make your case heard, it has to be that both
sides are there. This is a very like sort of insightful Rashi
here. All Rashis are insightful, but anyway, the Rashi here about six
lines before gets wide. שמוע בין אחיכם, shamoa bein achichem, Rashi says,
כשיבואו שניהם יחד שמעו דבריהם ולא תשמעו דברי זה בלא זה שמא
מסדר דברי שקר כדברי אמת. kesheyavou sheneihem yachad shimu divreihem velo sishmu
divrei zeh belo zeh shema mesader divrei sheker kedivrei emes. When somebody
is there and his his litigant is not in the same room,
he'll say his false claims as if they're true. He'll be more
prepared to just, you know, lie and present it as if so
this is the case, because לפי שאין מכחישו. lefi she'ein machshisho. nobody's
there to contradict him, ומכיוון שלב הדיין נוטה לו לזכות umikeivan shelev
hadayan noteh lo lizkot once the judge first hears that case first,
it's sort of like in what's it called poisoning the well or
the opposite, you know, whatever, it's priming the pump, you know, once
you've presented your case, that becomes the default lens through which the
judge hears it, even after they hear the other person's case presented
as well. שוב אין בו מהפך בזכות השני כל כך. shuv ein
bo mahapech bizchut hasheni kol kach. It's harder to be objective, because
it's already been presented and it's already, you know, been the first
way the judge has sort of the case.
Anchoring, that's what it's called. Oh, interesting. Okay.
So, that you
sort of
the first piece of information
anchors the way you frame the thing. Right. That's interesting. Okay.
But you can still have that somewhat. I mean, someone's going to
have to present first, but you know.
Yeah, but if the judge is there to arbitrate, and as soon
as you say something, you say, you know, you're already framing it
in your own mind as there are two versions. Fine, I've heard
now Michael's version, David, now tell me what your version of that
story is. So even when you say it, even if you had
to speak first, רש"י Rashi says you're not going to spin out
a total lie in David's presence, most likely, and B, in my
mind, I'm already framing it as there's another side to the story.
You know, a rabbi has to be very careful about this, too.
Somebody comes to share something with the rabbi, and they tell you
a whole story, which seems very persuasive or whatever. You have to
always remind yourself, this is one person's side of the story. I
haven't heard the other person's side. Right? But it's hard when the
other person isn't there to, you know, keep that balance.
Right, exactly. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, רב כהנא אמר מהכא, Rav Kahana amar meihacha, לא תשא שמע
שוא, lo tisa shema shav,
so do not, you know, lift up a false report or name.
So it doesn't just mean about swearing falsely, it means giving a
false story. לא תשי, lo tashi, which is also read as לא
תשי, lo tashi, which means not just don't be the one to
say it, but don't be the one to carry it, to receive
it as well. Okay.
לא תשא שמע שוא, lo tisa shema shav, אל תשת ידך עם
רשע להיות עד חמס. al tashet yadcha im rasha lihyot ed chamas.
Right. Not just against falsely, it's...
That's what I just said. It's not just about an oath. It's
about making a false report. Okay. ושפטתם צדק, u'shfatetem tzedek,
back to the פסוקים psukim by דברים. Devarim. Is this דברים? Devarim?
ושפטתם צדק בין איש ובין אחיו ובין גרו... לא תכירו פנים במשפט.
u'shfatetem tzedek bein ish u'vein achiv u'vein gero... lo takiru fanim bamishpat.
Yeah, this is דברים. Devarim. Okay. ושפטתם צדק, u'shfatetem tzedek, אמר ריש
לקיש צדק את הדין ואחר כך חתכהו. amar Reish Lakish tzedek et
hadin v'achar kach chatcheihu.
Justify the judgment, and then sort of cut it, then deliver it.
So it's interesting. רש"י Rashi didn't say exactly what the point here
was.
You know, does this just mean obviously go through the right process
of deliberation? Does it mean write out your reasoning and then, like
articulate your reasoning and then give the judgment? That's what it sounds
like, but you know, I have to tell you, in terms of
effectiveness, I think that works less effectively from the perspective of those
who hear it. Like, if you say, "Let me explain to you
why I'm about to rule the way I did, da-da-da-da-da, and therefore
my conclusion is X," right? That has less of a sense of
absolute, like bindingness. If I say, "Reuven is right. If you want
to hear my reasoning, you know, I'll write my reasoning afterwards," or
whatever. So it's not exactly, I wonder, did they give explanations there,
David, or whatever, somewhere what that צדק את הדין tzedek et hadin
because רש"י Rashi didn't really explicate what that means. No?
Only once the decision has been determined as the correct decision, righteousness
should be delivered as the verdict.
Wonderful. Meaning make sure you know what you're doing before you פסקן.
pasken. Right? Yeah.
Second in the United States, at least, always give a long explanation.
If you read Supreme Court...
Yeah, but that's after the judgment, the ruling. Meaning it doesn't precede
the issuing of the ruling. Right?
They actually read their decisions... but if the written decision, it says
in the beginning, it says what the
ruling is and the justification comes after. I think that's the way
you gotta do it. So if that's so, צדק את הדין tzedek
et hadin probably just means like make sure it's clear to you,
you know, before you issue the ruling, which is pretty obvious.
I mean, what I'm getting from this is, yeah, I mean צדק
את הדין ואחר כך חתכהו tzedek et hadin v'achar kach chatcheihu is
just like, you know, the ruling and not the deliberations. Like in
other words, we've had all the deliberations. Right? Don't give them the
whole thing because then they may learn, oh, if I had said
this...
So what does צדק את הדין tzedek et hadin mean?
In other words, first know what the end result is, you know,
what the פסק psak is, and חתכהו chatcheihu only give that part.
חתכהו, chatcheihu, like cut it off.
Just say what the ruling is.
Don't... So say the opposite.
All right, I don't know how that... I hear that. That's what
I would say, but I don't see exactly how that fits in
the words. But anyway, let's go on. בין איש ובין אחיו ובין
גרו, bein ish u'vein achiv u'vein gero, between one man and his
brother and his the sojourner. אמר רב יהודה אפילו בין בית לעליה,
amar Rav Yehuda afilu bein bayit l'aliyah, so בין איש ובין אחיו
אפילו בין בית לעליה, bein ish u'vein achiv afilu bein bayit l'aliyah,
even between the house and the upper chamber. What does that mean?
It means but we're interpreting אחיו achiv literally, a brother. Two brothers
inherit a house. So don't feel like oh, it's an easy case,
you get the ground floor, you get the top floor. No. Like
even in there, you have to do real justice. You have to
decide how much is each part worth and if there's a difference
in price, then the guy has to pay for the difference. So
don't try to sort of just summarily dismiss the case and just
say oh, we'll just split it.
to live even like
your furnishings. Don't just say, "Hey, you take the oven and you
take the stove" or whatever it is. No, one might be worth
more than the other and you have to figure out the difference.
Okay, לא תכירו פנים במשפט, lo takiru fanim bamishpat, do not recognize,
give favor to somebody because you know them and you recognize them.
רבי יהודה אומר לא תכירוהו, Rebbi Yehuda omer lo takiruhu, which is
the obvious פשט, pshat, don't sort of don't recognize somebody. But what
now but what seems to also be is saying is not just,
one way you could do it is like don't show favor because
you recognize them. But it could also just be like I know
a case about somebody who went to a בית דין Beis Din
for a גט, get, a woman went with her husband for בית
דין Beis Din for a גט, get, and it's one of the
בתי דינים Batei Dinim that is probably one of the better בתי
דינים Batei Dinim around. And but the story was that the husband
was like in ישיבה yeshiva with some of the guys that were
like on the דיינים. dayanim. You know the דיינים, dayanim, so he
walks in and they go, "Hey שלמה, Shlomo, how's it been a
long time? How's everything going?" or whatever. Now you know that very
thing made the woman feel like he is completely getting railroaded here,
right? And it might not have translated into anything, but the fact
that you show that you recognize somebody
has an impact on how the other side feel that they really
are being secure and having their case represented in speaking up and
so on. So just showing the recognition even without
favoritism can be a real problem.
Yes, I was considered for jury in Bronx County Supreme Court and
one of the reasons they kicked me off the potential jury pool
was that I told them that I actually personally knew one of
the judges.
There you go.
Okay, also they said in the Bronx Court, this was when they
were deciding who to be on the jury, that the judge, a
woman judge said, "don't say hello to me in the hallway" or
"don't offend me if I don't say
hello to you in the hallway". Oh, wow. They are very interesting.
So there you go, it's just sort of showing recognition of somebody
is itself a way that justice can get perverted.
Okay, רבי יהודה אומר לא תכירו. Rebbi Yehuda omer lo takiru. רבי
אלעזר אומר לא תנכרוהו, Rebbi Elazar omer lo tenakruhu, do not show
like, do not so do not like, like make him a stranger.
So if you look at רש״י: Rashi: אם הוא שונאך לא תעשה
לו כנכרי לחייבו. im hu soneacha lo taaseh lo kenochri l'chayvo. So
רש״י Rashi says it's like intentional, right? Do not like actually, do
not like if it's somebody you don't like, don't be biased against
him. But then it's just a straight point of try to remain
objective. In vein of what we were sort of saying before, it
could be the opposite. It could be like, if,
like is there a way of, let's say I do know Michael,
okay, and I'm the judge. So I shouldn't go and say, "Hey
Michael, how's everything going?" but I shouldn't go out of my way
to sort of treat him like I have no idea who he
is. Then he might actually feel the opposite, that he's going to
be biased against me, right? So it's striking that balance
of, "oh hello" and say it like, so don't show him a
welcome but don't also make him a stranger either. Okay, then now
we have a story. אושפיזיניה דרב אחא
דרב, Ushpixineih de'Rav Acha de'Rav, so the host, like the innkeeper where
רב Rav was having his lodgings, אתא לקמיה לדינא, ata lekameih l'dina,
came to רב Rav for a judgment. אמר ליה, Amar leih, so
he saw רב Rav and he said to רב, Rav, לאו
אושפיזיני את? Lav ushpixini at? So, "Hey aren't you my, don't you
have a room in my inn? Oh I know you!" So אמר
ליה, Amar leih, "אין" in he said yes, actually I do I
am taking rooms in your inn. So אמר ליה דינא אית לי,
Amar leih dina is li, so then the innkeeper said, "okay but
now I have a judgment I need a case I want to
bring to you." אמר ליה פסילנא לך לדינא, Amar leih psilna lach
l'dina, well you just have disqualified me to be your judge because
by and apparently, it's because you raised the point. It wasn't the
fact, I mean, I'm paying for the lodging, it's not like you're
doing me some favor. תוספות Tosafos says, if we look at תוספות:
Tosafos: פסילנא לך, psilna lach, right, well first רש״י Rashi says: שהזכרתני
טובתך, shehizkartani tovascha, you mentioned it. If you hadn't mentioned it, it
wouldn't have been a problem, but that's like לא תכירוהו, lo takiruhu,
right? By surfacing it, that creates a problem. And תוספות Tosafos says:
מרחיק הוה עצמו אבל מן הדין לא מיפסל, marchik hava atzmo aval
min hadin lo mipsal, וכן הוא דשני דייני גזירות דאייתו ליה צנתא
דפירי. vechein hu deshnei dayanei gezeiros d'ayisu lei tzanta d'feiri. So he's
saying it's not real שוחד, shochad, it doesn't really invalidate you, but
we're not here talking about the question of שוחד, shochad, we're talking
about this issue of לא תכירוהו, lo takiruhu, more about like procedurally
that is not
appropriate once you mention that connection. So okay. אמר ליה רב לרב
כהנא, Amar leih Rav l'Rav Kahana, so top of ח, ches, רב
Rav said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, פוק
דייניה, puk dayneih, go so now that רב Rav couldn't be the
judge, he said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana
you go take his case, I can't be the case, פוק דייניה.
puk dayneih. חזייה דהוה קגאיס ביה, Chazeih d'hava kaga'is beih, so רב
כהנא... Rav Kahana... So that this innkeeper was acting a little bit
too
comfortable with Rav. Oh yeah, it's great, Rav! Yeah, I just gave
him, I served him eggs this morning, he was over yesterday night
whatever like he was feel like trying to show how thinking that
he was going to win this case. Okay, אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so Rav Kahana said to him, אציתא אציתא. Itsaisa itsaisa. Listen buddy,
if you pay, if you obey, obey meaning show proper deference and
so on and know that you do not have any special access
here, ואי לא, Ve-i lo, and if you start continuing acting like
a wise guy, a little bit too comfortably, נפקנא לך רב מאונך,
Nafkina lach Rav me-onecha, I will pull Rav out of your ear.
Okay, which basically means I will put you in חרם. Cherem. If
you look at רש"י, Rashi, אודיעך שאין רב יכול לסייעך, Odiacha she-ein
Rav yachol le-sayiecha,
I will make it clear that Rav can't come to your aid.
דמשמתינא לך, De-mashmetina lach, I'll put you in חרם Cherem and then
it'll be clear that you are in disfavor of the court. Okay,
a finding of contempt of the court. Okay,
now going back to the פסוק Pasuk in דברים, Devarim, כקטן כגדל
תשמעון, Ke-katan ke-gadol tishme'un,
like the small and the great one you should listen. אמר ריש
לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, שחביב עליך דין של פרוטה כדין של מאה
מנה. She-chaviv alecha din shel peruta ke-din shel me'ah maneh. So small
case and a big case, not only a small person, important person,
person who's not socially important. No, small case and a big case.
So the גמרא Gemara says treat equally. למאי הלכתא? Le-mai hilchata? למאי
הלכתא? Le-mai hilchata? אילימא לעיוני ביה ומיפסקיה, Eilima le-iyunei bei u-mifskia, if
it means to give it proper deliberation and judgment and to be
as careful in how you judge the case, פשיטא, Pshita, obvious. Now,
it might be obvious from a הלכה'דיק Halachadik standpoint, right? But it's
not obvious from a human psychological standpoint, right? If I'm dealing with
a multi-million dollar case as opposed to a case of fact ten
dollars, which one am I going to give more time and effort
to assess? But the גמרא Gemara says, well
okay, but הלכה'דיקלי, Halachadikly, obviously justice is justice. Right? So if so
obviously that you have to treat equally, אלא לאקדומי, Ela le-akdomei, no,
to tell you that even if it's a question of which one
to deal with first, that whichever comes up first is first. It
doesn't, you don't put aside dealing with the case of ten dollars
to deal with the multi-million dollar case first. לא תגורו מפני איש,
Lo taguru mi-pnei ish, do not fear any person. So we already
quoted before if you want to read the parentheses, אמר רב חנן,
Amar Rav Chanan, אל תכניס דבריך מפני איש, Al tachnis devarecha mi-pnei
ish, doesn't just mean don't fear, but don't keep your words,
don't hold your words back if you're like a clerk or whatever.
כי המשפט לאלהים הוא, Ki ha-mishpat le-Elohim hu, because justice is to
God. אמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chama be-Rabbi Chanina, אמר
הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, לא דיין לרשעים. Lo dayam
la-resha'im. And it's just a play on דיין Dayan and דין. Din.
לא דיין לרשעים שנוטלין מזה ממון ונותנין לזה שלא כדין, Lo dayam
la-resha'im she-notlin mi-zeh mammon ve-notnin le-zeh she-lo ke-din, it's not enough for
the wicked, and here the wicked are the judges, not just the
thieves, who take from from this person and give to another one
against what justice should demand, אלא שמטריחין אותי להחזיר ממון לבעליו, Ela
she-matrichin oti le-hachzir mammon le-ba'alav, and this goes back to the גמרא
Gemara that you're actually when you judge incorrectly or you testify falsely,
you're judging against God because now you're demanding you're leaving it as
my responsibility to rectify, to clean up your mess or your perversion
of justice. והדבר אשר יקשה מכם תקרבון אלי ושמעתיו, Ve-ha-davar asher yiksheh
mi-chem takrivun elai u-shmati-v, and something that is too difficult for you,
bring to me and I will hear it.
ושמעתיו. U-shmati-v. So אמר רבי חנינא ואיתימא רבי יאשיה, Amar Rabbi Chanina
ve-eiteima Rabbi Yoshiya, על דבר זה נענש משה. Al davar zeh ne'enash
Moshe. Ah, Moshe was punished for this taking like this, oh if
it's too difficult bring it to me, okay so he's sort of
setting himself as the ultimate arbitrator, right? He doesn't say like I'll
ask God, he says I'll hear it. So he says על דבר
זה נענש משה, Al davar zeh ne'enash Moshe, שנאמר ויקרב משה את
משפטן לפני ה'. She-ne'emar vayakrev Moshe et mishpatan lifnei Hashem. So they
did it, something they brought to Moshe and he didn't have the
answer. It was shown so it was just to show don't don't
set yourself up even if you're משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, don't set
yourself up like you're the like you have always will have all
the answers.
Refers you to a more knowledgeable judge.
Exactly. So מתקיף לה רב נחמן בר יצחק, Matkif lah Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, מי כתיב אשמיעכם? Mi ketiv ashmi'achem? It doesn't say bring
it to me and I will tell you what the ruling is.
ושמעתיו U-shmati-v כתיב. Ketiv. So meaning I will hear it. Now הפשט
Ha-pshat probably is I will hear what you have to say and
decide correctly, but the גמרא's Gemara reading it as I will hear
from God what the ruling is. Okay, when you bring it to
me. אי גמירנא גמירנא, Ei gemirna gemirna, if I know the ruling
I'll tell it to you, ואי לא, Ve-i lo, and if not
אזלינא וגמירנא, Azlina ve-gemirna, I'll go and I'll learn it, I'll hear
it from God. So therefore Moshe didn't do anything wrong and the
fact that it was בנות צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad and he had to
ask from God was not a punishment to him, was not a
way of puncturing him, puncturing whatever the statement. So what why was
it then that he went to God? So הגמרא Ha-Gemara says אלא
כדתניא, Ela kide-tanya, ראויה פרשה נחלות שתיכתב על ידי משה רבינו. Re'uya
parashat nachalot she-tikatev al yedei Moshe Rabbeinu.
Moshe really could have just straight given it, it didn't require בנות
צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad to come to him, right? Because this is also
the גמרא Gemara dealing with the problem like and if בנות צלפחד
Benot Tzelofchad had never come about so never would have been written?
Which is certainly what it sounds like in the פסוקים, Pesukim, but
obviously from the גמרא, Gemara, from a theological perspective that's hard, like
if this is God's תורה Torah then God would have issued it
anyway. So you know what you're right, if there had never been
בנות צלפחד, Benot Tzelofchad, sometime within the 40 years God would have
given Moshe the commands of women and inheritance. אלא שזכו בנות צלפחד
ונכתבה על ידן Ella shezachu Bnot Tzelafchad venichteva al yadan
but they merited because they spoke up for what needed to speak
up and so on. The way it worked out was that it
was written as a result of or in the context of them
asking the question.
Exactly. But had they never asked, God would have issued this ruling
as well. Okay, ראויה היא פרשת מקושש שתכתב על ידי משה רבינו.
Reuya hi parshat mekoshesh sheticatav al yedei Moshe Rabbeinu. Similarly the idea
of the guy who gathered the sticks on שבת Shabbat and the
תורה Torah tells you what the punishment would be, that if that
event had never occurred, God would have, you know, it would have
been written anyway what the punishment would have been for חילול שבת.
Chilul Shabbat. But אלא שנתחייב מקושש ונכתבה על ידו, Ella shenitchayev mekoshesh
venichteva al yado, the same thing, the way things worked out was
it got told in the context of this שבת Shabbat violator and
it was written, you know, in response to him. But it would
have been written anyway.
ללמדך שמגלגלין חובה על ידי חייב וזכות על ידי זכאי. Lamedcha shemegalgelin
chovah al yedei chayav vezachut al yedei zakai. That those that deserve,
you know,
are guilty, bad things will sort of fall upon them, and those
that are meritorious good things will happen. So you know, because this
guy was a מחלל שבת, Mechalel Shabbat, he got remembered for having
a whole פרשה Parsha about the punishment of חילול שבת Chilul Shabbat
written for him, which is like, I mean it's good that we
know the הלכה, Halacha, but the fact that he's associated with this
פרשה. Parsha. And the same with בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzelafchad, you know,
this would have been written anyway, but because they stood up for
their rights, their father's rights, they did it in the right way,
they approached
משה Moshe correctly, they had this whole פרשה Parsha attributed to them.
It's interesting with פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. Now that's true. Okay. Okay, דכתיב Dechtiv now back to
the פסוקים pesukim in דברים. Devarim. ואצוה את שופטיכם בעת ההיא, Vaatzaveh
et shofteichem baet hahi, I commanded your judges at this time. וכתיב
ואצוה אתכם בעת ההיא, Uchtiv vaatzaveh etchem baet hahi,
I commanded you at this time. So who's משה Moshe commanding, you
know, them or the judges? So אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי שמלאי,
Amar Rabbi Elazar Amar Rabbi Simlai, אזהרה לציבור שתהא אימת דיין עליהם.
azhara latzibur shetehei eimat dayan aleihem. Both. The ציבור tzibur has their
responsibility, they need to have the proper honor and respect and fear
of the judges. ואזהרה לדיין שיסבול את הציבור, Veazhara ladayan sheyisbol et
hatzibur, and the judge has to actually deal with
the complaints and bear the burden of the ציבור. tzibur. Okay, because
שמוע בין אחיכם ושפטתם צדק בין איש ובין אחיו ובין גרו לא
תכירו פנים במשפט כקטן כגדל תשמעון. shamoa bein acheichem ushfattem tzedek bein
ish uvein achiv uvein gero lo takiru fanim bamishpat kakatun kagadol tishmaun.
ואצוה אתכם בעת ההיא את
כל הדברים אשר תעשון.
Vaatzaveh etchem baet hahi et
kol hadevarim asher taasun. Right.
Well, whatever. Anyway, right. Okay. עד
כמה, Ad kama,
to what point do you have to deal with all their friction
and all their burden? אמר רבי יוחנן ואיתימא רב שבתאי, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan veitayma Rav Shavtai, כאשר ישא האמן את הינק. kaasher yisa haomen
et hayonek. As,
you know, like a crying baby you have to be their nursemaid.
Okay.
Now what is that משה Moshe complained
and
he got שבעים זקנים shivim zekenim though? I know. What is that
line from Mother Teresa? You know that line? What is it like,
you know, something about like, you know, people are petty and this
and that and like love them anyway? Nobody knows that line? I
know. It's very heretical this שיעור, shiur, I'm quoting Mother Teresa.
If you would have quoted a פסוק pasuk in תורה Torah I
could
have.
Yeah. Hold on.
There's a good רש״י Rashi like, רש״י Rashi is like, you know,
by
רש״י Rashi sort of says, טרחנים הם. tarchanim hem. By, you know,
there's a רש״י Rashi out there that basically says that. Here. איכה
אשא לבדי טרחכם
ומשאכם וריבכם.
Eicha esa levadi tarchachem umasachem
verivchem.
What? Yeah, what's that רש״י? Rashi? Read that
רש״י.
Rashi. מלמד שהיו ישראל טרחנים היה אחד מהם רואה את בעל דינו
נוצח בדין. Melamed shehayu Yisrael tarchanim haya echad mehem roeh et baal
dino notzeach badin. One would see the other, you know, victory in
Torah. אומר יש לי עדים להביא יש לי ראיות להביא מוסיף אני
עליכם דיינים. Omer yesh li edim lehavi yesh li reayot lehavi mosif
ani aleichem dayanim.
No, no, no. There was another רש״י Rashi which is טרחנים הם,
tarchanim hem, whatever something like that. Okay. Anyway, this שיעור, shiur, this
is one version of it, but there's a better one.
People are unreasonable, irrational, self-centered, forgive them anyway. So anyway, there's a
better version of this. Okay, whatever. Moving on. Okay, there's also a
good רש״י Rashi on that. All right, anyway, I'll find it. All
right, where are we? Okay. כתיב, Ktiv, כי אתה תבוא, ki ata
tavo, by משה Moshe speaks to
יהושע Yehoshua it says you will bring this people, or you will
go with this people into the land. וכתיב, Uchtiv, כי אתה תביא,
ki ata tavi, you will bring them. So which is it? Are
you just going along with them or are you leading them? אמר
רבי יוחנן אמר לו משה ליהושע אתה
וזקנים שבדור עמהם. Amar Rabbi Yochanan amar lo Moshe leYehoshua ata uzekeinim
shebador imahem. You go with the elders, you're not just the leader.
So that's what משה Moshe said, כי אתה תבוא את העם הזה.
ki ata tavo et haam hazeh.
And the end of the פסוק pasuk says, to the land that
God had promised them. So that clearly wasn't משה Moshe's voice. So
he said אתה תבוא. ata tavo. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar
lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu, טול מקל והך על קדקדם. tol makeil vehach
al kadkodam. No,
don't be so humble. You're the leader, take the staff and bang
them on the head. אתה תביא. ata tavi. You have to show
strong leadership. דבר אחד לדור ואין שני דברים לדור. Dabar echad lador
veein shenei debarim lador.
One leader for the generation, not two. So even though משה, Moshe,
he's not you, it's יהושע, Yehoshua, but that doesn't mean that he
rules together with the זקנים. zekeinim. You know, people need a leader
to own that leadership. You know, maybe he consults with the זקנים,
zekeinim, but he's still the leader. אתה תביא. ata tavi.
Because they'll climb on his head.
I understand. Okay. תנא זימון בשלושה מאי זימון. Tana zimmun bishlosha mai
zimmun. תנא זימון בשלושה. Tanna zimmun bishlosha. מאי זימון בשלושה? Mai zimmun
bishlosha? What does it mean זימון zimmun is with three? אילימא ברכת
זימון, Ileima birkat zimmun, ותניא זימון בשלושה, ברכת זימון בשלושה. v’tanya zimmun
bishlosha, birkat zimmun bishlosha. So we know that. וכי תימא פירושי קמפרש,
V’chi teima pirushay kamperish, so זימון zimmun is different from ברכת זימון.
birkat zimmun. וכי תימא פירושי קמפרש, V’chi teima pirushay kamperish, מאי זימון
ברכת זימון? mai zimmun birkat zimmun? It’s really saying one thing. ותניא
זימון בשלושה, ברכת זימון בשלושה. v’tanya zimmun bishlosha, birkat zimmun bishlosha. There’s
something different. ברכת זימון, Birkat zimmun, which is benching, is three, but
there’s this other thing called זימון. zimmun. What’s this other thing that’s
not ברכת זימון? birkat zimmun? אלא מאי זימון? Ella mai zimmun? What
does זימון zimmun mean? אזמוני לדין. Azmuni l’din. When you have something
having nothing to do with benching, when you’re coming to call somebody
to the court, it has to be through the בית דין, Beit
Din, three judges.
So does that mean you need three people to summon you?
Well, no, well, three people, well, you’ll see. כי הא דאמר רבא,
Ki ha d’amar Rava, like Rava said, הני בי תלתא דייני דיתבי
ואתא שליחא דבי דינא. hanei bi tlata dayanei d’yasvi v’ata shelicha d’bei
dina. So a בית דין Beit Din is sitting and a messenger
of the court goes, ואמר משמיה דחד, v’amar mishmei d’chad, and summons
somebody to court and says, "I am calling you to court in
the name of judge X,"
okay, one of the judges, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, then
he does not really represent the court and you don’t have to
respond to the summons, עד דאמר משמיה דכולהו. ad d’amar mishmei d’chulhu.
When he is issuing a summons, the זימון, zimmun, being summoned by
the court, means he’s saying, "I’m issuing it by the entire court,
by all three judges." Okay. הני מילי בלא יומא דדינא, Hanei milei
belo yoma d’dina, but that’s when it’s not actually the day of
justice judgment, meaning it’s not a Monday or Thursday, רש"י Rashi says,
the day the court is sitting. אבל ביומא דדינא, Aval beyoma d’dina,
if it is a day that the court is sitting, so משמיה
דחד, mishmei d’chad, then saying in the name of one judge does
not, is not a problem because it’s understood to mean in the
name of the sitting בית דין, Beit Din, and therefore it’s always
understood to mean in the name of the בית דין. Beit Din.
Okay, so we will end with that.